so we're recording today's
topic for solution raising is war as
eric mentioned before we started
recording i
am picking big topics that feel too big
to tackle the solution raising
um i don't know i don't know what we're
going to come up with um
i'm going to start with just a little
bit of a definition of war like i don't
think whatever we're creating is going
to end all violence
i mean war very much as one government
going to war with another government it
also feels
like there's maybe some civil war about
to happen in the world
and i don't know if that that might come
up when we're talking i don't know what
the solution is we're going to come up
with whether it's something for civil
war or something
whether we can even tackle it so this
part is the part where we
share what the world currently looks
like and can vent about
war in general because it's basically
been around for all of human existence
so it feels like it's something that we
couldn't possibly not have as humanity
much like poverty and i think that we
can get to a world where
it's not the norm that our governments
go and slaughter other people
but that's just my utopian ideals
i mean i'll i'll get us started just as
i so often do and just sort of
try and provide or sort of explore a
little bit of context around the world
because war is a continuum right i mean
all that warfare guns pointed at each
other
missiles blah blah blah blah i mean all
of that that's that's all out kinetic
warfare but i mean warfare can happen
between two individuals as well right a
feud between two people
like you and your sister could be said
to be at war with each other to some
degree right and
and so you know this this exists across
all scales and at all levels of severity
and it's kind of a
mindset it's uh it it it emerges from
the us and then mindset right if there
is no then there's no one to go to war
against and so it's
it's it's sort of an inevitable
consequence of
the notion of othering and the notion of
othering runs very very very deep
because i mean this is one of the way
game a
works right is you create loyalty to
your culture and one of the primary ways
of doing
that is to create antipathy and fear
towards those who are not
our culture and so this this is very
very deep in our social programming
um so yeah i mean tackling war as you
said at the start jubilee
no way obviously you can tackle war on
the level of governments firing missiles
at each other right there's no way this
this runs but possibly within the domain
of the solution raising
is going some way towards
oh i don't know showing how to get to
other mindsets
at a less grand level maybe something
like that
something like that but yeah wars
everywhere is basically what i'm saying
we are at war with each other
in all kinds of ways all the time
yeah and i think that's an important
point i do think we can tackle this at a
government level in fact i think it's
much easier somewhat to tackle as a
government level even though we don't
have the power on the government level
um then at a personal level right to
solve all conflict that ever arises no
but they're
similar and i think that what you said
about the othering and the becoming um
that a lot of what we're seeing is this
othering like if you're a mask wearer
then you look at the people who aren't
wearing masks because they're all
selfish they're all horrible
um and like that someone can actually
represent an entire group right if
you're in game b
i just had someone because of my mlf
idea be like this might show badly on
all of game b
i'm like i don't know if you know like
it's like
but and that's like realizing when we're
talking about a group of people and when
we're talking about an individual
that if there's a group of protesters
and one throws a brick in
how do you know it's how do you know
it's um
part of your group even right even if
someone is doing something that's bad
how do you know which group they're part
of it's so easy to have an
asian provocateur come in and disrupt
things and that isn't war
but it's war it's like that's how we get
to war it's how the civil war might
be coming about with the election in the
states like
that there's these other people who are
doing evil and they're not acting like
me
and i'm gonna put them all into one
group and when one of them acts badly
it's all of them right one must or a
handful of muslims
uh flew a plane into a tower and it
collapsed so now we have to go to war
with with all the middle east
well so they say so they say
and so that is yes that there is to me
tackling it at the
government level is more attacking at
the attacking it at the corporate level
that if we are not making landmines and
weapons of mass destruction
and weapons huge planes and drones and
doing that
then there is no war like if people have
to only go after each other with what we
did in world war one
it's a different level than having this
this gross technological advantage where
you can like
you know have people in them in the west
having
control over drones going to kill other
people and doing all of these things
that are done for profit we can see that
it's done for profit and part of my
event also that i definitely need to
put in here is this idea we have about
soldiers that they're heroic that
they're there
to to like well america like we gotta
like look after america it's like is
that actually what you're doing these
people weren't coming to invade you
you're invading them
and enforcing your values on other
people and i see it in canada all the
time too when it comes to november 11th
which is our remembrance day
and like oh look at everyone who fought
for our rights it's like did they
did they fight for our rights is that
actually what happened that's the
rhetoric
that's the and the people who go into it
i think are there for good reasons i
think they actually
are growing i want to push back a little
bit here i want to push back a little
bit here jubilee because i mean
while i completely agree with you the
reasons that the soldiers were sent to
war had nothing to do with honor and
and nationhood and all that well
nationhood to a certain extent but
you know but
the individual soldiers
are acting absolutely out of a sense of
honor and duty you know what i mean
or most of them anyway you know people
people don't and this is one of the
it's good actually that you because this
has reminded me of the the
one of the truly evil things about our
culture is that we
take that nobility and bravery and
willingness to sacrifice yourself for
your brother and for your
tribe or nation or whatever it might be
right though the you know
the the most um
uh the highest traits that we have as
human beings
taking that and turning it into
acquisition of land money do you know
what i mean like and telling
so it it it's it's
i don't know it feels like an
abomination on a
biblical scale right to take to take the
most
sacred divine highest
things of which we are capable and
turning them into the basest
parts of our nature right there there's
something really really really horrible
there that war
embodies yeah absolutely matt i'm going
to invite you if you would like to to
also
share what you think of war currently
i'm just going to go get my kid to
be a little quieter i only heard of that
so she hasn't been bold
at once well uh
first i think war is bad war bad
anyway no but uh what's coming to mind
is um
i don't know have you guys seen um the
social dilemma
yeah there's a netflix documentary and
you know tying that in with daniel
schmucktenberger and his
you know war on sense-making and
information warfare and how our limbic
systems are being hijacked and how
you know each of us has a personalized
algorithm
that can beat gary kasparov at chess
that's trying to beat us and you know
maximize our time on site and
you know polarize us uh
in our in our views towards our our
fellow humans
um that
i think is the war that's taking place
um and i think that's kind of
almost the generator function to what is
what is is causing the um
rules yeah yeah or or at least at least
now the
the kind of impending civil war that
could
take place because i mean everyone wants
to kill each other and everyone thinks
they're right and everyone is so
you know extreme and if if
you were to change the you know
incentive structure for these silicon
valley companies
and you know take their black box
algorithms and
pop them open and change them um
i think you would see a lot of this
stuff subside
um i think it would be like you know the
storm clouds disperse
and sure i think some people would still
be radicalized and whatnot but
i mean if we don't fix that
there is no hope in trying to
um find solutions
so i think any salute any solution
will look like
something in the form of
building alternative sense making
networks with different technologies
that are not built upon
existing technology stacks of silicon
valley
or regulating
the existing um silicon valley companies
which i don't know how the hell you're
going to do that i don't know how you're
going to do that
especially when you can target all of
the regulators
and sick gary kasparov
on them and mess up their sense-making
apparatus
how are you going to get the policy
makers to make sense
of the problem well enough to actually
change
how are you going to get the people on
board so it's a it's a very hard problem
to solve
um if there was a genie here and then
you could grant me my wish i would say
you know bring these bring these giants
to their knees
but i don't know how you do that yeah
but you see the thing is other giants
just pop up in their placemat that's the
problem and because these are systemic
problems right these
these individuals the jeff bezos and
whatever of this world are just playing
roles
in you know a drama because the the
structure demands certain individuals to
play those kinds of roles right
you know but people that call for their
heads and whatever i i get it you know
what i mean i mean i get it i feel it
too right
yeah yeah it doesn't it doesn't actually
accomplish anything
how do you think you you've hit the nail
on the head that until
you can create an environment in which
people who have
you know people of good faith earnestly
hold different opinions about stuff and
be
and a space in which those differences
of opinion can be explored and figured
out and
and maybe some kind of synthesis come to
you know what i mean
until the circumstances exist for that
to happen and my god are we a billion
miles away from that at the moment
um yeah then you're absolutely right
nothing else is actually a solution all
it is
is something that one camp puts up and
it gets fought over and gets adopted or
not but whichever happens half of the
people
are pissed off about it you know i'm
curious though you brought up an
interesting point you said you know like
okay if we
you know if we bring facebook to their
knees and google to their knees
you know jeff bezos is going to come
along and just spin up another one
and capture everybody's minds again and
so
if that's a reality and then on the
other hand
uh it's a reality that um
the existing sense-making frameworks
that people are subscribed to
make it difficult to uh make these
policy changes and these legal changes
how do you where's the hope what do you
do
how do you how do you make it exactly
sorry i just the hope is exactly the
kind of thing you know that jubilee and
many others like
are doing is building stuff from the
ground up
and simply replacing them right but
you know it's it's a slow it's a slow
thing and it's a snowball kind of thing
and it does require
it requires people who it requires
people to actually participate in it
right not to talk about it but actually
participate in it and
what and and hopefully hopefully at some
point
all of these things all of this space
which is being explored by all of these
people trying all of these different
things out hopefully at some point
all of those threads start to converge
on a common attractor
and and something coherent and big and
powerful and
and with reach and with a user base and
influence and so on you know what i mean
that emerges from that
because cultural capital is is the thing
these days right i mean economic capital
is actually secondary these days to
cultural capital you've got an audience
if you've got people who will listen to
you that is more powerful than having
all the money in the world these days
it is true and i think that is like that
we
worry about the big powerful people the
governments the
the technology more than like people
would rather sit around
and complain about that than show up to
a solution rating
that's a bigger problem and it's not
because i don't think they don't want
it's they don't know they exist
and they don't they're like like you
know there were five to ten people who
were interested in this session that's
why i thought we'd have more
but it's like they're like war we
couldn't possibly so why even tackle it
right and it's like
do i know that's why they didn't show up
no but that feels like
like they're like what arrogance that
you think you can solve war in an hour
in fact i just went
and shushed my kid right i was like
we're trying to solve where she's like
you're not selling more
i think it's hard for people right now
and i mean if you if you look at
at i mean people are are
literally plugged into the matrix here
you know on
on whatever on their social media feeds
and it
it's really hard to you know
rip yourself away from that and you know
i don't know i mean it's it's tough for
people so
you've got it takes a great deal of
discipline i mean daniel talked about
this right and if you think about two
people one in
in say portland and one in say texas
right the guy in portland
or the woman in portland or whatever
he's getting this non-stop feed of black
men shot by police black man assaulted
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah right
was the guy in texas is getting
black man assaults white police officer
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah right and and so
you know this is all they see this is
what they think the news is right and so
no wonder they're up in arms against
each other because
i don't you want me you cats
you're killing one black person after
another with impunity no
you you're assaulting
police officers for no good reason
you know what i mean and and it's no
wonder these people are at each other's
throats you know it's not it's not
actually their fault you know
they they've had their whole view of
what's going on in the world
narrowed down to that and
and it's not their fault they've they've
been right
it's like it's like when i said it it's
like um
you know they give this analogy a lot
but it's like
everyone has this personal algorithm
that is better than gary kasparov
at chess so everyone that wants to come
to the solution raising meetings
they have to beat gary kasparov at chess
just to unplug and get some mental
clarity
and to push through their anxiety
push through their depression push
through everything
just to show up and not be crippled with
anxiety and like
talk and not want to fight or be filled
with contention in some ways
are you saying what's actually happened
is they've all been distracted by porn
or gambling or catholic pictures or
whatever
is that what you're saying or just or or
just like they're they
had to come but other things just
distracted them before they got here
yeah their limbic system has been
hijacked
so that is part of our problem is it's
less like
you do we have a social media problem
abso-frequently but everyone is trying
to solve it is trying to solve it for
the like
unwashed masses instead of for
themselves like you can unlock
right and if there's a very big
difference between
creating something that is voluntary
that is invitational
and creating something that is like this
is the salute right like
this is how we make sense so everyone
needs to make sense this way instead of
asking
how do you make sense how can we have
that same newsfeed how can we know
what's
actually going on in the world without
changing it to us versus them
how do you actually know what is
happening and um
and i'm sure we could talk about this
and rant about our current state of
affairs and war for
for more than an hour but i will invite
us because we're almost at the half an
hour mark
to share our beautiful vision of the
future where we have solved war and what
does that look like
it means that the conditions for violent
conflict
no longer exist and the violent conflict
is no longer incentivized in any way i
mean really the single most profitable
activity that you can engage in in this
planet is war
i mean in the in the tanks and missiles
and ships sense i mean
you know it is the single so you know to
have
an economic market system that actually
incentivizes
this activity above all is is somewhat
absurd so
clearly war doesn't end until but
to a certain extent i mean i don't know
what you guys think about this
because you can't unring these bells you
can't uninvent the gun you can't
uninvent the nuclear
device you know what i mean once these
things have come into the world they're
they're in the world for good and so
how do you go about managing that
because in a world that is free of
weapons
the one man that has the one remaining
gun has complete power right so
you know how do you i mean that's the
ultimate prisoner's dilemma isn't it
because people have guns stashed and
hoarded and in basements and blah blah
blah blah blah buried all over the
place right so
how do you deal with that problem
because obviously a world without war
the
the perfect the you know the beautiful
future doesn't have people shooting each
other doesn't have people going to war
doesn't doesn't have people entering
violent conflict conflicts are resolved
in constructive ways before it ever gets
that far
right and and but how do you stop that
handful of residual guns which because
there are no others make them
super duper duper super powerful
yeah so we'll definitely discuss i don't
know if you can
but what does the beautiful world look
like where we have done that
right maybe we don't maybe we did
destroy every last gun well then we can
3d print them
so that's nice that's what i mean you
just can't un-invent you can't you can't
just pretend that these things don't
exist in the world
then once they're here they're always
here and so you have to live within that
reality right so yeah maybe it isn't
possible i mean
maybe there will be always be however
well everything works and however good
everyone's life isn't however much you
can
you know there's no constraints on you
know what you can do other than not
going around killing people there will
might
may always be the old person who for
whatever reason
wants to go around killing people maybe
i don't know i don't know
i'll share my beautiful version of the
future which is you're right we can't
necessarily
get rid of every last gun but where we
definitely stop mass producing
um the weapons of war the missiles the
tanks the planes stuck
stop putting massive amounts of money
into that stop bombing
cities when that makes no sense and
there isn't um
systemic war there isn't our governments
going to war with each other because we
can see
that makes no sense not economically not
environmentally
it makes rich people richer and it makes
everybody else pay the price
in the most horrific way and to be able
to have access to that sense making
apparatus that we know what's going on
in the world and what's being done in
our name and because of
us without being able to turn that blind
eye without being able to say oh my
my choice to buy this computer means
there is a
maybe a war going on in africa i don't
know but like
that those things are more more visible
that we are connected on a global scale
so that when there is war somewhere we
are witnessing it and truly witnessing
it
because we all have cell phones and most
places that are going through war have
cell phones even if they don't have cell
connection
and finding the ability to witness each
other and be able to say this is what's
happening
it can't be spun because we've um or it
can be but
when we've dealt with the agent
provocateurs in a way that we know they
exist and
we're working within that system we know
our sense-making can be with
so let's deal with that let's deal with
like right how would we know it's true
and then creating that instead of
relying instead of you know three people
getting together and creating a new
source that we want 7.5 billion people
to look at
how do 10 000 people come together and
create a new source that they trust
and then they can extrapolate that to
the rest of the population that is what
these
these are about so that's a bit of it's
definitely zero war my very beautiful
world
has zero governments going to war
because their citizenry will not stand
for it
so will there be one person who is like
hey i know what we can do and takes up
violence
absolutely and they might even be able
to get a tiny group of people
but when people aren't in poverty and
they're not being squished by
by the powers that be constantly you
cannot get an army of people
to take over someone else because what's
the point
you're just going to destroy resources
not create them you know like
as much as right now in the middle east
it's a lot of
islam that's creating war right like
it's a lot of um it isn't
it's the poverty it's the it's the
like if if
people are looked after they cannot be
made into murders they cannot be made
into terrorists no matter what your
belief system is
um it's you can you get anyone yeah of
course you can get someone
but you can't get hundreds and thousands
of people together and so that is
anyway a bit of my beautiful future
i would just say my beautiful future
looks
isn't isn't very grandiose it's
i just kinda wanna see things maybe like
one percent better
and then go from there maybe then we can
do two percent
three percent but let's get that one
percent under our belts first
um and yeah i mean i'd like to see
a world where
i mean this feeling of civil war
is very visceral to me right now and
i see it in relationships with
family friends loved ones and
if we don't fix what's
generating that then um
it's gonna get pretty ugly so i think
that's kind of what's at
the top of my mind right now but uh
all right thanks matt uh now we can
switch over to the part where we
actually saw things
what could we do with ten thousand
people and a hundred thousand dollars
and um
tackle war and i think that we could
tackle it from either end we could
tackle it from the governmental end
of tracking where they're spending money
and what companies are spending money on
the fact that this widget's worth ten
thousand dollars when it freaking
clearly is not the fact that
this drone like tracking the actual
what's happening that these people are
being killed this place got demolished
this place
and doing it in a way that is um
trustworthy
that isn't done from fox news isn't
creating it the u.s government or
canadian government isn't creating and
it's us creating it
or tackling it from the other end like
you said being my sister a little bit of
war
what would it look like to solve that
what would it look like to
deal with okay i have this tension that
people don't want to wear masks and
other people
you know like what does it actually look
like because mandating them clearly
isn't the answer that's why we have this
and yet there is this division and there
is an effect that one group has on the
other group
both um mainly stress both groups cause
stress on the other person which is the
worst thing you can do in a pandemic is
cause a bunch of stress on people
because it makes them more susceptible
to any disease having
that conflict resolution at the
individual level that is voluntary
having conflict resolution at the bigger
level of like mastery not masquerading
where can we find our common ground how
would
how do we both get our needs met both
groups without
demonizing each other and saying you're
the worst of the worst because you feel
differently than me
creating those to any of those tools i
think would be powerful
yeah i mean i don't know if this helps
this is just this is a very personal
example
um and around kobe seeing as how we were
talking about kobe this is actually what
i was going to
talk to you about later but you'll have
a little bit of thinking time now
um but it fits very well here so there's
a person that i play glass b
games every week we've come to know each
other pretty well i've known each other
for a few months now come to know each
other pretty well
we have could not be i don't think much
more diametrically opposed
viewpoints on the whole kobe thing and
you know the
measures being taken by governments and
blah blah blah blah blah blah
pretty much every part of it we we
disagree with each other
from opposite directions but we are both
reasonable intelligent people of good
faith and we are going to use this as an
opportunity to do kind of exactly what
you said
and try some conflict resolution at an
individual level because our last
discussion although there was no
animosity right there's no hard feelings
but it did get quite
heated and i certainly felt in myself
and i expect jen felt the same way i
felt a certain agitation right which
means that there's something there
that i need to deal with right i don't
know exactly what it is but there's
clearly something if i'm getting
emotional
during the course of this discussion
when i have no
you know personal investment in it right
so why is it bringing up emotions so
anyway
the modality we're going to adopt is
we're going to have
three discussions the first one she's
going to explain why
she thinks how she thinks and i'm going
to have the opportunity to ask questions
not argue with her
but ask questions so that i can gain
complete clarity
and understand so that i can explain
back to her to her satisfaction
that i have understood where she's
coming from right
then we'll have another conversation
where exactly the opposite will happen
right she'll do the same with me
and then we'll have a third and final
structured like a glass speed game right
where we take turns we take two minute
turns
and we hash it out now that we've fully
understood where the other person is
coming from
assuming that there is still
disagreement it's possible that that
process
will lead to synthesis
understanding and no further need to
argue anymore because
we get it and we've arrived at a place
that we're both happy with right maybe
but if not then a
structured argument if you like
taking two minute turns each listening
carefully having already fully
understood the other pair
and see what that brings i mean i don't
know we haven't started embarked on this
process yet we've agreed on a bit
happening box on it yet
but that's beautiful sorry sorry matt go
on i'm done
oh no i just said that's beautiful
that's incred i think it's i think it's
incredible that
that you're doing that with another
human i think if we all
if we all made that step that's all we
have to do to get us out of this mess
if if we all just took that
utmost personal responsibility in saying
i could be right i could be wrong but
the important part is
there's no way i'm wrong
we're doing this so she can see i'm
right i mean clearly this to convince
it's just a big trap that's what it is
it's an elaborate trap
perfect and i think that that is um like
i with together tech with bentley and
adriel's projects
of um sense making and bentley is doing
reason score which is all about having
an actual
intellectual debate and getting the
evidence on your side
and um there's something that that's
missing that you're talking about and
something also that that gives that this
doesn't
it's like a debate's not going to work
because it never really convinces
somebody on one side but it does get you
clear more on the information
and the logical side without the
fallacies and the papayas
and then dealing with that emotional
is the bigger part of like wait why
do i feel
so horrible that you're not willing to
wear a mask or that i am
wearing a mask or whatever it comes out
to right that their government
like you think that if people are
voluntarily wearing masks that somehow
the government
has way more power and you know like
these kind of things and so to be able
to see it from somebody else's side
is powerful and to be able to offer that
to the world to be able i know in the
game b
space i'm becoming less of an admin in
the bar is like great you two have a
video conversation you're
misunderstanding each other you guys
need to get on an actual conversation
because this isn't going to work this
back and forth and i try to hold that
when i'm feeling tension with somebody i
try to reach out
and have a real conversation because it
has always been a powerful learning for
me
and it generally repairs the
relationship there's only been two or
three times out of the dozens i've done
it
where i'm like oh my god no you really
are an idiot right or like i come out
more
like it doesn't it doesn't saw i'm not
like oh yeah i see the beauty in you i'm
like i don't you just are never gonna
see this like i just don't want it
well this is this is another thing and i
mean this is clearly something that
speaks to something in me right because
um
my and i can't help feeling i'm not
saying it's right but i can't help
feeling that anyone that does
buy into yes we should stay at home we
should keep our kids home from school we
should wear masks you know what i mean
all of this kind of thing
i can't help feel that these people have
been emotionally and intellectually
hijacked and to a certain extent are
being willfully ignorant
of a whole bunch of information they're
choosing to ignore
in order to hold that position because
if they were to actually admit
that information in then they couldn't
possibly hold the opinions that they
hold right and so i it it
it irritates me that people see some
scenes and and so
this is this is where my irritation
comes from and i i don't think jen is
like that i don't think you're like that
right and so
you know yeah there is something in me
as well as the argument itself there is
also something in me which i need to
find that is reacting to all of this
yeah see i i maybe i forgive me if i
sound like a broken record but
well sorry what was your name jen is
that yeah
yeah so here's the thing in my
view you know ideology aside and whether
or not you're pro mask or
or against masks you if if you're for
masks you know
okay let me let me figure out a
different way to say this um
the way people have formulated the
opinions
that they've um that they've come
to is through essentially social media
and internet right and
they're subscribed to various feeds that
are
controlled by algorithms that
have an interest in getting them to
believe certain things
and we've already established that these
algorithms
are way better than me way better than
you and way better than
her at
they're being used against her and so
you're
you're playing with that algorithm
that's
that can beat gary kasparov at chess and
so to think that you're going to change
somebody's mind
any progress that you make um
the night the minute they go back on
social media and they go
you know you know they they consume
their information
it's going to kind of muddy the waters
and
you know and kind of pollute it but that
makes that's equally true of me right i
mean
exactly exactly yeah who i follow on
facebook and blah blah blah blah not
that i do have followers of anyone on
facebook
but yeah no i mean that that's it's true
of all of us right and this is this is
the key point is for us to
at an individual level recognize that
whether we believe it or not whether we
like it or not almost certainly we have
been hijacked right and and you know
and and just accepting that even though
i don't believe i've been hijacked i
believe that i have a balanced view
right i i truthfully believe i have a
balanced view and that i have
actually looked at and listened to
people from a wide variety of different
viewpoints and different camps right and
have a good understanding of
a broad spectrum of the arguments that's
what i think but
who knows i could be completely
deceiving myself right and that what i
watch has led me
quite deliberately to that conclusion is
self-satisfied
smug yeah yeah yeah there's nothing
there's no argument you have that i
haven't already heard kind of thing
which is which is which is a bit how i
feel so there is there is an arrogance
that resides in me i'm i'm i'm hoping i
can get underneath i'm really hoping
that jen can
open something up to me which i really
truly hadn't seen before which does
change my whole feeling and view of it
this is this is
actually my hope i mean i was joking
before when i said the whole point i'm
going into this is to change her mind
right but i was only half joking
i mean there is a big part of me where
and i feel it and i know and i admit to
it
that that is my desired outcome right
and and i can't help that that's
i'm not proud of it you know what i mean
it's not my highest angels
but there is a big part of me that is
what i want from this but
my but my higher angels which is what is
prompting me to undergo this process
wants to be changed and transformed by
it right thereby validating the power
of the process right the the and
of my own ability to actually go into it
with a mind open enough that it's
willing to be changed
there's something that's coming up for
me while you're sharing about this which
is like this
arms race that exists in debates right
where it's like i can
i can win because i'm smarter and i have
because either side could win right the
mask debate or the non-mask debate the
virus
the government the virus versus the
government is the government
overreaching yes can we argue with a
virus no
like that there's there's both sides to
it um
and yet it's this arms race of like
there's like omega rule omega rule can
only be invited not invoked right i
can't demand omega rule from you i can
only offer it to you
or and request maybe that you use it
with me but i can't demand it
and that there are tools that like undo
the arms race that are like that
right that there's a certain level that
you and jen are willing to get together
and have this glass speed game is
awesome
what if she wasn't right there's a
certain amount
yeah absolutely your own inner
right when you're willing to show up and
be like
i know there's a part of me that's
acting like a toddler right now but i
don't know what to do about that
and you're willing to grow right because
i know i've constantly feel that energy
i'm like this is this feels like a
tantrum more than a
more than productive but if i go into
any conversation to learn what i'm there
to learn
i come out better it doesn't matter what
the other person does and the more we
can create systems that are like that
that are like this isn't an arms race
because i'm practicing omega rule this
is
doing the admin part is like they're not
i'm like they don't need to that's not
the rule
you can practice it and you practice it
to the nth degree means that they don't
need to
that's the irony and so that there's
something broken about a debate because
it's like
you can win it or lose it whereas
there's something beautiful what you
guys are doing
even if someone wins the debate which
isn't a debate
if you go in with the intention of you
learning then you come out better and
that's all that needs to happen
and so dealing with that inner tension
and inviting people to because there's
the other side that happens that i find
which is
this arms race of knowledge i think i've
told the story about the salmon when i
was in university
i looked into farm salmon and it turned
out neither side wanted to do the actual
really cheap
experiment that would prove whether the
lice from the farmed salmon were hurting
the wild salmon and neither side wanted
to do it because they didn't want to
find out they were wrong
and it's like that same level of
ignorance happens time and time again
where it's like are you here to get the
truth are you here to be right
are you here to and yet there's um that
like you have to lie on a job
application because everyone else is
lying on a job application so if you
show up in our truthful you're gonna
look worse
and so there's something that that you
do we just have to show up and tell the
truth
and allow the culture to catch up even
in
this ecosystem of facebook and google
and amazon
it's like right they're just
perpetuating that but we can create
something better
that is invitational that
it doesn't matter what the other people
are doing it only matters what you're
doing and that's the problem with the
mask no mask debate
is it truly does matter what you're
doing right whichever side you're on the
people who are wearing that do you
sheep you're letting her uncomfortably
oh maybe maybe maybe it doesn't matter
at all whether you wear a mask or not
you know what i mean
this is what i mean even even when you
try to be like open and reasonable
assumptions come into your speech right
you can't help it
so yeah you know it is it is super
difficult it is super difficult
yeah i'm afraid to talk about this
subject
masks
the the whole it's a it's a it's a
minefield i mean it's not it's
it's probably even worse now
a minefield than you know the gender
debate or even the race debate i think
the kobe debate is even
you know it's oh my god people it's
maddening
really it's you know either
absolutely everything the government
says it's a complete big stinking pile
of you can't believe any of it
and
don't trust those and i have
some sympathy for that view
i do but nevertheless it's extreme and
absurd right
and equally everything they say is being
told to us in good faith based on the
best information that they have and yeah
they're not perfect but you know they're
doing the best they can
that also is rubbish right i mean both
of those are absolutely nonsensical
positions to hold
hey eric can you can you put a mask on
right now i don't want the droplets to
come through
[Laughter]
i've got like seven of them in my
bathroom cabinet because every time i go
out
i forget to bring my mask right because
i mean i live in the middle of the
country i
never ever ever have to wear a mask
except once a month i go shopping kind
of thing
and every time i go i forget my mask and
i have to buy another one or scrounge
another one or someone whatever
and so i've accumulated seven masks now
in my bathroom cabinet
i went home to uh to uh california a few
months
back and uh every time i saw my mom she
was just stuff in my pockets with masks
here here take more take more
i'm on the side of biology i'm a
biologist and i understand that we don't
understand this virus and it's brand new
and do i trust governments no i
don't even trust the scientists because
i don't think i think they come out of a
very broken game a system and we can't
trust them
i also know that based on the statistics
because i understand statistics
like people are taking the number of
people who are infected
dividing that by the number of or the
death by that number be like look it's
only killing one and
less than one in one percent and that's
not the math the math is the people
who've recovered
divided by by the or the total people
that have been infected and recovered or
died
the people who died divided by that and
that shows over five percent and that is
a deadly disease
and so it's like that these are the kind
of things where it's like but they lied
to us they told us to wear them they
told us not to
and we can see the information ecology
playing out in real time
it doesn't matter what kind of side
you're on everyone's actions affect
everyone else whether you're wearing
their whether you're not
whether it's affecting more people or
less whether it's spreading whether it's
not
our actions impact each other in a very
real way
and yet can we get everyone's needs met
right i know we're kind of getting off
topics we're talking about masks instead
of war
but this is our current board but we are
at war over masks
or whatever this is this is a perfect
example of non-kinetic warfare going on
in the culture i mean this is part
this is one one battle being fought in
the culture
right one of thousands of different
battles simultaneously and then it feels
like the battle is is like well we need
our governments to mandate masks and
it's like that's not gonna work or we
need our governments to step the
off and let
everyone walk around naked with coffee
on everyone it's like
can we get our needs back can we do it
without mandating because then it's
about truth and sense making right what
is the truth of this virus the truth is
science is never black and white
and different things affect people
differently but though you end up with
lynch mobs on the street people going
around with baseball bats demanding
people wear their masks right
yes exactly and that's what that's the
level when there's no official policy
and people
aren't used to taking responsibility and
self-governance and all of that kind of
thing when people aren't used to it you
can't just foist it on them and expect
it to work you know what i mean
it's about somewhat what is the word
segregation
like allowable segregation
and this grocery store is no masks and
and but then how do you deal with
workers because workers are different
how do you deal with people
who are highly susceptible yeah
yeah so then you have an hour for them
to shop
something that the way i look at it is
kind of like like again this
to strike at the root i think this all
comes down to
how the kind of information ecology
works in our
um in our world and kind of how the
existing
institutional structures that that have
you know taken control whether that be
you know governments or the federal
reserve or the cdc
or these these these institutions are
not exactly open source
um and there's not uh very
great ways of information verification
uh there's an expression uh that goes
around a lot in the
in the um blockchain cryptocurrency
space and it says
uh don't trust verify
so in a lot of these cases when we
find out information about whether
that's covid
or financial data or whatever
how do we even know where that came from
or or whether or not that's accurate or
or i have to trust
trust some institution to tell me the
specifics
of the molecular makeup
of the virus and this and that it's like
okay i might not be a biologist or a
virologist or whatever
but i can find other biologists and
virologists that i
trust that can get that open source
data and verify it and until we have
kind of that system of checks and
balances
to even test this information
empirically i see the whole debate over
masks as just
it's it's nonsense it's nonsense we need
it we need to strike
deeper and and figure out this stuff
at the root before we even start
debating whether or not we should wear
masks or not
because we don't know what the hell is
going on yeah and that's the level when
i was talking about an arms race
like we could debate that and i could
you know bring out this scientific
good i don't know but like bring up this
scientific study in this scientific
study you could and one of us would be
better and one of us would win that
debate
but it's not getting to the heart of
what you're talking about right which is
like how do i
know the truth and i don't think we can
trust our governments and the powers
that be right now
that i know and so i understand why
people don't want to wear masks and i'm
not even so sure
i like it's like right that's not
necessarily the most effective thing
i get annoyed every week when i watch
big brother because the people come out
and when they come out of the house with
13 people in it who've been sequestered
for months they have to wear a mask but
the host doesn't
i'm like i don't think you understand
what the you're doing like it's
like she should be wearing the mask
not the contestant coming out but these
are the kind of things where it's like
is it
is it a security blanket that just makes
me feel better or is it to protect the
other people around me
and anyway we get mixed information
mixed information from the scientists
from the media that the media is wearing
masks and they don't wear it here and
it's just
it's ridiculous and it's that
information ecology that we have to get
to
not this idea of like you need to do
your research well no because it doesn't
help you know much research i've
done
a hell of a lot of research about my
disabilities about about biology because
i
happen to have that as my degree and it
doesn't help because i have to deal with
a world of people who doesn't understand
it right well and you can find
math biology you can find studies to
support whatever your view is yeah
so it doesn't matter so unless you
unless you
strike at the root and find just that
initial way of verifying information
period unless you do start with a
premise that you believe in right and
then you hunt for information that
supports it and
then yeah yeah yeah yeah absolutely
absolutely and as you say you can find
pretty much something to support
anything like have you seen the you know
are you familiar with james lindsay and
all those yeah yeah yeah
i mean like look case in point they can
just make whatever they want
up and publish it and then somebody uses
that
what i can't remember the word was but
some of them got like commendations
right like exceptional work kind of
work outstanding yeah
yeah i don't even know what we're
talking about but like dogs like like
one of the studies was like somehow like
saying that like
dogs uh propagated like rape culture or
something
in dog parks and so we should ban dog
parks or something like that so
it's just it's just it just shows how
it's so easy to pollute
the information ecology it's so easy to
subvert it
and and so how profoundly polluted it
already is right i mean how little you
can
you yeah you just can't trust you can't
really trust
anything there is the problem
i think that so how do you build an
epistemology when it is impossible to
find reliable information how the
do you go about making any sense of
anything
and have any faith in the scentsy i mean
really you can only go
by your own personal experience and
build networks so that you can
add to your own personal experience the
personal experience of other people whom
you trust
to relay that experience with high
fidelity and that has to be your sense
that has to be your sense sense-making
web and anything that that is outside
the boundaries of that well
sorry that's just mystery can't know
anything about that
i think i i actually watched this a
couple weeks ago it came across my feed
it was a video
that uh jordan hall did on
on his youtube channel you know how he
does those little uh yeah little bits
where he just
uh uh explained some kind of theory or
concept
um and one of them was talking about
things similar to what we're talking
about about how
everyone just the whole information
ecology and he was saying
he was kind of likening it unto
the invention of the atomic bomb and and
that's what we're dealing with here
we're dealing with
this atomic bomb like magnitude
of of destruction
in the information ecology so
at least that's that's what i got out of
it but and i'll send it to you guys it's
interesting
daniel i haven't listened to jordan's
talk on that but daniel schwab talked
about that a lot and i don't disagree
that we should be looking at how we're
polluting the information ecology
but also it doesn't really help
like it doesn't help so much to not
pollute it because it's so polluted we
have to deal with it as it's polluted
like we know there can be deep fakes we
know that there's going to be bad actors
and we know there's going to be good
actors acting in bad ways and bad actors
got in good ways
how can we make something we can trust
right which is very different than
how do i make something all of you can
trust you can't because i don't trust
you
it's right there no now is this what
they're talking about then that's also i
haven't heard that part of
daniel's thing but i'm like right but
it's very different if it's designed for
jordan and daniel
who have a high sense making capacity
anyway versus
not designed for them not not designed
for them it's designed kind of as a news
network right so as a broadcast news
network with a broadcast news network
which
has used um high
functioning good faith earnest people
working together as a collective network
to fact check and cross-reference and
synthesize
and sew on information put it in the
correct historical context all of this
kind of thing and you know
and so rather than having to read 20
books in order to
gain the necessary context to properly
understand this
information they will have people who
will condense all of that context into a
manageable document so that you can
with reasonable um
ability to make sense of it access this
information in the proper context right
this is the thing i mean information
prevention
and sometimes context understand you
know to understand the context you might
need to understand 500 years of history
to properly understand the context of of
this thing and so as well as the story
you get and so this is what he's working
on and then so you generally you know
providing proper curated
checked relevant contextualized
information
which god is because that is much
similar to what i came into the game b
space looking to create
at the same time depending on what that
who an expert is it can hurt it or help
it because if you have to have a degree
in physics be able to talk about physics
then you have to have gone through a
university degree in physics which means
you're already co-opted by the system
instead of you having learned it
yourself you know i mean like those are
very different so what you need is
someone with a degree in physics who can
understand the work
that has you know the research paper
that's being because a layman can't
access the research paper right but then
you also
need some you know informed let me have
some understanding in the field enough
that that person can then translate this
into a form that they can understand ask
questions make sure they've got the
point of it
and then they can translate it into the
language that the rest of us can
understand sort of things
but see i think this is what this is
what i think
um john verveigh and guy seng stock
and a lot of these people are doing
with the concept of dialogos
and because we don't know if we're gonna
get
this you know special news broadcast
network or whatever
that that they're talking about creating
but but
i think what we're doing here is a form
of
deal logos and i think what you're
attempting to do with jen is
is that you know because we each
have a piece of the puzzle and we each
have a corrupted piece of the puzzle
and if we can come to the table using
rule omega
and hash this out let me clean this off
a little bit for you
you clean this off for me and we'll kind
of polish this nice
sphere of information and
it it it completes it you know it's like
the uh it's like the uh the power
rangers
getting together or captain of captain
planet remember that
everyone brings a piece of the puzzle
and they'll summon
anyway but everyone brings a piece of
the puzzle and then it it forms this
much more perfect more powerful force
to make sense of things but anyway
all right i know we got off topic for
the majority of what we were talking
about but not off topic because it was
very much in no it was a super
interesting discussion i really enjoyed
it absolutely
um i would like to still do what we
usually do at the end though which is
what do you think is the most powerful
thing we can do
to move towards peace away from war and
towards peace with ten thousand people
and a hundred thousand dollars
yeah i mean we never even really talked
about that um
yeah no idea really with the ten
thousand people a hundred thousand
dollars but i i guess some way of
encouraging
people to take more time and put more
effort into
understanding that with which they
disagree
not to agree with it right but just to
understand it and understand why
somebody else might think that way right
even without ever
any hope of agreeing with it ever or
even coming to a higher res
you know agreeing to disagree when you
actually both truly understand each
other i think is okay i don't think
there's anything wrong with that
and that's unlikely to cause conflict
right because you understand why you
disagree with each other you've been
through it so yeah i mean it doesn't fit
in the ten thousand hundred thousand
thing but but that's
that's the key i think something like
that oh yeah i think i would say
i would say kind of a variation mine
would be the sim very similar to that
and
be kind of almost
drop your opinions drop your beliefs
and just go try to talk to somebody
and just try to understand them fully
and be friends with them and try to push
all of this stuff aside push it all
aside and
and just befriend somebody
you know and i think if we all just did
that
you know one percent of the time it
would make everything a little better
thank you matt um my most powerful one
that would go towards creating peace i
think
is similar to what daniel is creating
having a sense making apparatus that we
can trust
and use gets us a lot of the way because
we don't then have to have that
constant debate and or having a system
that is conflict resolution
similar to what eric and jen are doing
but facilitated by
technology right where you can invite
someone to that right you don't have to
have
them necessarily have the level of
personal evolution or whatever it is
that makes them aware they can do that
and both willing to sit down that
there's various levels and even
potentially conflict resolution even if
it's one party
right so if i want a conflict resolution
the person i'm in conflict with doesn't
there are ways i can still deal with
that conflict
that are going to get it out of my body
and my learning out of it that don't
require the other person and having
those things available so you know where
you can go for those
for those tools and don't tell you that
you're right and they're wrong yeah okay
good thank you
[Laughter]
the opposite of that like finding your
learning in it and not needing
to admit it to them the more the more
you can just go ahead and believe it and
not have to deal with that
absolutely okay i'm gonna end the
recording now and then
bye youtube